<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before His Majestie at Christ-Church in Oxford, on the 18. of April 1643. By William Stampe vicar of Stepney in the county of Middlesex.</title>
            <author>Stampe, William, 1611-1653?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5194</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E101_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11010</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858921</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858921</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155877</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93780)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155877)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 18:E101[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before His Majestie at Christ-Church in Oxford, on the 18. of April 1643. By William Stampe vicar of Stepney in the county of Middlesex.</title>
                  <author>Stampe, William, 1611-1653?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[H. Hall],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from Madan.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 8.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah LIX, 1-2 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155877:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155877:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before His MAIESTIE AT CHRIST-CHVRCH IN OXFORD. On the 18. of April 1643.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM STAMPE Vicar of <hi>Stepney</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed in the yeare 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:155877:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155877:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST ILLVSTRIOVS PRINCE, CHARLES PRINCE OF WALES, DVKE OF CORNWALL, and Earle of CHESTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath pleaſ'd your Highneſſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand this Sermon to the Preſſe, and mee to be your ſervant: what you have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd from either, that might incline you to ſo much grace and favour, I know not; unleſſe it were my plaine
<pb facs="tcp:155877:3"/> dealing with the Times. This (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) your Highneſſe mentioned with a deep ſence and reliſh. Would God the madde world knew it. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it were enough to ſtop the foule mouthes of ſome: enough to warme the honeſt hearts of others. God Almighty ſo compoſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent troubles of this State, that the Government thereof may ſtand the ſurer for this ſhaking; and continue and increaſe his graces in you for the glorious ſupport thereof, when it ſhall pleaſe him to lay it upon your ſhoulders.</p>
            <closer>Thus prayes <signed>Your Highneſſes moſt obliged humble ſervant, WILLIAM STAMPE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155877:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED before His MAjESTIE at <hi>Chriſtchurch</hi> in <hi>Oxford</hi> on Tueſday, the 18 of <hi>April,</hi> 1643.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ESAY 59. 1, 2.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>1 </bibl> Behold, the Lords hand is not ſhortned, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſave, neither his eare heavy that it cannot heare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>2</bibl> But your iniquities have ſeparated betweene you and your God, and your ſinnes have hid his face from you that he will not heare.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the precedent Chapter, we have the difference ſtated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a religious, true faſt; and that which is merely fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitious and Hypocriticall. In this, we have the true ground why our faſtings at ſome times become fruitleſſe, and our prayers unſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefull: Both common theames; yet neither of them unſeaſonable as our times now are. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155877:4"/> did any age produce more faſting, more preaching, more praying. Never did theſe holy exerciſes produce leſſe fruit. Looke we well up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the fruites, and we muſt be driven to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude (by an argument a <hi>poſteriori</hi>) that ſure ſome where or other, there hath been <hi>faſting for ſtrife, and debate, and to ſmite with the fiſt of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay 48. 4.</note> for of theſe bitter and accurſed fruits have wee abundantly taſted, witneſſe every Cranny and Corner of two miſerable diſtreſſed King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: So that our devotion hath neither pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented Gods Judgments: nor (which is worſe) Gods Judgments prevented our ſinnes. What betweene the Atheiſt in heart (the ſchiſmaticall, factious, &amp; diſſembling Hypocrite;) and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt in profeſſion (the licentious, daring, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved ſinner) we are yet to faſt, and yet to pray, and yet to proſper, and prevaile with God: wee are (at beſt) but under the throes and pangs of our deliverance; not, but that God is as eaſily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated at this day as ever he was ſince the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; his power and propenſitie to releive <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> is as great (at this day) as ever it was to releive his owne peculiar <hi>Iſraell.</hi> The great incapacity we labour under, is from our ſelves. <hi>Gods Controverſie for ſinne,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſ 4. 1.</note> is the Cauſe of all our Controverſies among our ſelves; his Mercy and Juſtice are as immutable as himſelfe, and therefore if wee are not relieved, wee muſt not blame him, but thanke our ſelves. For <hi>Behold
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155877:4"/> the Lords hand is not ſhortned, &amp;c.</hi> This <hi>Text</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by the Prophet, to prevent a miſtake which Commonly ariſes in the hearts of men, in their conceipts of God, and themſelves. For if we want what we would have, or feele what we would want, we rave and ſtorme, and impute the <hi>troubles of Iſraell</hi> ſometimes, to <hi>Ahab</hi> the King, ſometime to <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet, nay ſometimes we pin them on God himſelfe; and inſtead of <hi>humbling our ſelves under his mighty hand,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Pet 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have our ſelves very frowardly in his covenant</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 44. 17.</note>.</p>
            <p>For the prevention of which, this text hath a double aſpect, with one eye it lookes upwards upon Almighty God, and there takes notice of an omnipotent <hi>hand,</hi> an attentive <hi>Eare,</hi> both poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at with an <hi>Ecce, Bebold the Lords hand is not ſhortned that it cannot ſave: neither his eare heavy that it cannot heare,</hi> with the other eye it lookes downeward, upon man: upon man at diſtance from his maker, upon man divorceing himſelfe from his God, and (by a ſelfe Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) delivering himſelfe up into the power and government of Satan. So that we have here <hi>Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid Dei,</hi> and <hi>Aliquid noſtri:</hi> that which belongs to God, deſcribed in the Negative, <hi>his hand is not ſhortned, his eare is not heavy, &amp;c.</hi> (that is) he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies one and the ſame God: That which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to us, (and which indeed wee can onely call our owne) are our ſins; and not barely ſinnes but Iniquities too; and theſe with two deſperate
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155877:5"/> Conſequences following cloſe at the heeles; one is, <hi>they obſcure the light of Gods favourable Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 16. 26.</note> the other is, they make a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and us; they make us (that which is ſo odious in the very name) <hi>Seperatiſts;</hi> and of all <hi>Seperatiſts</hi> the worſt, <hi>Seperatiſts</hi> from God. Theſe are the naturall parts of the text, wherein I ſhall breifely diſcover Gods power and propenſity to releive his people, and afterwards enquire into theſe 3 particulars. 1. What it is that ſeperates from God 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Wherein God ſeperates from us, 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. (which reſults from both) in what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition we are when God is depated from us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold the Lords hand is not ſhortned, &amp;c.</hi> The words are a large propoſall of mercy offered to all that will but make themſelves capable of it, namely, that God hath alwaies an attentive eare, and a ready hand, to releive thoſe that ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe themſelves unto him. Not that God hath either <hi>Hand or Eare</hi> in ſtrictnes of ſpeech, in both <hi>Humanum dicit,</hi> he ſpeakes to us (as the nourſe to the child) in that language, wherein we are beſt able to underſtand him. Nor is it a ſingle mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that is here propoſed, but mercy inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated; not <hi>hand</hi> alone, or <hi>eare</hi> alone, but <hi>hand</hi> and <hi>eare</hi> both: not an <hi>Hand Shortned,</hi> or an <hi>Eare heavy:</hi> but an <hi>hand</hi> ſtretched out, an <hi>eare</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies attentive. So that wee can no ſooner pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent a prayer, but God immediately meets it with his eare, and whilſt the prayer is even en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155877:5"/> into his eares, he meets and embraceth with his hand of mercy.</p>
            <p>Againe, the mercies here propoſed are of two ſorts, either Spirituall mercies, ſuch as concerne the inward man; or Temporall, ſuch as concerne the preſervation of the outward: in both theſe reſpects <hi>the hand of the Lord is not ſhortned.</hi> As for ſpirituall mercies, I ſhall onely ſay thus much in briefe, that God (in that Covenant of Grace which hee is pleaſed to make with his Creature) freely offers unto us his ſonne, and in him all the Treaſures of inexhauſtible mercy: No otherwiſe then a <hi>King</hi> by his Proclamation <hi>Royall,</hi> offers his mercy to thoſe rebels, that will but throw <hi>away</hi> their Armes, and come in and ſubmit themſelves to him, and his Government. But as thoſe Proclamations are ſeldome without the Proviſo of a limited time: ſo Gods mercies have their dates upon them; which if once expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, they are no longer mercies, but the heavy doomes of wrath and Judgement; like the ſame exhalation which diſtills at one time in a ſweet; ſoftning ſhowre; and at another time, by being detained too long, is hardned into a thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolt. To the old world he gave a time of 120 yeares <hi>Gen:</hi> 6: 3: To the Citie of <hi>Nineve</hi> a time of 40 daies, <hi>Jonah</hi> 3. 4. To <hi>Jezabell</hi> a certaine ſpace to <hi>repent of Her Fornication, Revel:</hi> 2: 21: To every ſoule <hi>Horam prafixam,</hi> a certaine limited time <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 7. And as he gives his word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155877:6"/> to the ſea, <note place="margin">Pſal. 104. 9.</note> thus farre thou ſhalt come and noe farther: ſo his word is gone out concerning every one of of us here preſent: Thus long my hand ſhall not be ſhortned unto you, Thus long yee have the Scepter of my mercy held out unto you: Thus long I am content to wait, and liſten, to heare but ſo much as a <hi>Quid feci,</hi> come from you: <note place="margin">Ier. 8. 6.</note> But not a minute longer then the limited time, the glaſſe is turned upon you, and there's no reverſing the ſentence after it is once pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced. We know they were all virgins in the parable, and all of them alike <hi>ſlumbered and ſlept,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 1.</note> only the fooliſh ones, ſtayed a little beyond their limited time. The time is, when God may and <hi>will be found:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 55. 6.</note> The time will be, when God cannot, <hi>will not be found;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 1. 28.</note> when his hand will be ſhortned and his eare heavy &amp;c. and then he that is <hi>filthy ſhall be filthy ſtill,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Revel. 22. 11.</note> and <hi>he that is unjuſt ſhall be unjuſt</hi> for ever. <note place="margin">14. 13.</note> And becauſe <hi>Non eſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strum, &amp;c.</hi> It is not for us to know when this time ſhall be. How thrifty ſhould we be of thoſe houres, which are but given us to prepare for that houre which neither <hi>Men,</hi> nor <hi>Angells</hi> know of? How ſeaſonable and welcome ſhould that hand of mercy be: which (like our Saviours un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Saint <hi>Peter</hi>) offers at this inſtant to ſave mee from an eternall <hi>drowning?</hi> How precious and invaluable that moment, that gives me either a <hi>Bene</hi> or a <hi>Male Diſceſſit</hi> to all eternitie? That part of time which is paſt, will never wheele about a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155877:6"/> that which we thinke and preſume is yet to come, may peradventure never come, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly time we can call our owne is the preſent, as yet <hi>his Hand is not ſhortned, neither his eare heavy:</hi> It ſhall be our wiſedome therefore, to make Gods time, our time, the time of his Grace: the time of our Reconciliation: and let this be thought upon at all times: That he that neglects the preſent time, in hopes of future, does for the preſent forſake his owne mercy: and ſhall ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly find himſelfe for the time to come, more hardned, more unworthy, if not uncapable of that mercy he hath ſlighted.</p>
            <p>2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> In regard of Temporall preſervations his <hi>Hand is not ſhortned,</hi> &amp;c. The ſame hand of mercy which was a Convoy to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Sea<note n="a" place="margin">Exod: 14. 2.</note>, a Crane to <hi>Joſeph</hi> in the pit<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 37. 28.</note>: to <hi>Ieremy</hi> in the Dungeon<note n="c" place="margin">Ier. 38. 13.</note>, A protection to <hi>Daniell</hi> in the Den<note n="d" place="margin">Dan: 6. 23.</note>, to the three children in the furnace<note n="e" place="margin">Dan: 3 27:</note>: The ſame hand that had the <hi>windes in his fiſt</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pro: 30. 4.</note> in 88: The ſame <hi>Digitus Dei,</hi> that pointed out that horrid, (though now we cannot ſay unparrallel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) Conſpiracie <hi>Novemb.</hi> 5: The ſame hand that ſaved a Crowne, <note place="margin">The Battell at Edge-hill.</note> and ſheltered the Royall bloud Octob. 23. (at the apprehenſion of which hazard our Trembling will be, (and our praiſes ſhould be) as ſtrong and laſting as our memories.) The ſame Canopy of good providence and protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on does as yet hang over us, if we doe not runne away from under it.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:155877:7"/>
            <p>And as it is with the <hi>Hand:</hi> ſo is it likewiſe with the <hi>Eare;</hi> Certainely the Eare of the Almighty was very free, and open to our forefathers: that <hi>Joſhuah</hi> and <hi>Hezechiah</hi> could command the Sun to <hi>ſtand ſtill</hi> or <hi>goe backe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioſh 110. 12.</note> as they ſhould direct: That <hi>Elijah</hi> had ſo much power over <hi>Iſrael</hi> and the Elements, <note place="margin">2 King. 20 10.</note> that there could be <hi>neither raine nor dew for three yeares, but onely at his word:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 King: 17 1.</note> And that <hi>Moyſes</hi> had ſo much power in prevailing with God, <note place="margin">Numb: 16.</note> that he is intreated of God, not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat for the people. And yet Saint <hi>James</hi> will tell ye theſe were but men: <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am: 5 17.</note> men, <hi>ſubject to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame paſſions, and infirmities with any of us.</hi> Our ſinnes have made all the difference that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene us. <hi>Behold his eare is not yet heavy, &amp;c.</hi> The Sunne is alwaies of the ſame ſtrength, and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, notwithſtanding an Ecclipſe, or interpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Cloud: The needle of the Compaſſe leanes alwaies to the ſame point, be the weather never ſo foule, or the diſtance never ſo farre. Gods power is like the Sunne, allwaies in full ſtrength, <hi>there is nothing hid from the heate thereof:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal 119 6.</note> his propenſitie to helpe, like the needle of the Compaſſe, leanes alwaies one and the ſame way: But we miſtake our God, becauſe we miſtake our ſelves; and (with the giddy apprehenſions of thoſe that put to Sea) we thinke the Land goes away from us, when the truth is wee goe away from it.</p>
            <p>God is an Eternall, and Immutable eſſence, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155877:7"/> two armes of his Mercy and Juſtice, of equall dimenſion and extent: never ſo ſtrict in Juſtice, but alwaies mercifull: never ſo Gracious in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie but alwaies Juſt. Nor is it poſſible he ſhould bee otherwiſe at any time, then what hee hath beene from all Eternitie. <hi>Behold the hand of the Lord is not ſhortned, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Doctrine of Gods immutability, laies a ſtrict charge upon the pulpit and the preſſe, to be faithfull and impartiall in thoſe meſſages that come from God. Our doctrine ſhould not bee like the water in the weather-glaſſe, that riſes and falls according as the winde ſits. If God be alwaies the ſame, why ſhould not his word be ſo too? There is not under heaven, a more ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and deformed creature then a changeling in the pulpit; And what ever men may hope to gaine, or ſave, in deſperate, and unſteady times; by wreſting that which was never made to bow, <note place="margin">The Scripture.</note> yet, ſure I am there's one text in Saint <hi>Iohns Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> will not be wreſted; That to the bold uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per on Gods word, (either by <hi>Addition</hi> or <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution</hi>) <hi>God ſhall adde all the plagues that are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in that booke, and ſhall take away his part out of the booke of life. Revel</hi> 22, 18.</p>
            <p>And (in the ſecond place) it would bee no ſhame for the zealous <hi>Sectarie</hi> to reforme the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate errour of his way; who is now <hi>Ieſuite</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to contract, or dilate the Hand of Gods mercy, according as he ſees the purſe open, and ſhut, to the cauſe and himſelfe. He makes great
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155877:8"/> uſe of the Devils perſpective; whereof hee hath one end for the Pulpit, and another end for the Chamber. This in the Pulpit ſhall preſent mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy contracted, or (like the character hee writes in) in ſhort hand; That in the chamber ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it both vaſte, and neare; and under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Chriſtian Libertie,</hi> or ſomething that muſt go for zeale, ſhall inſtruct ye to ſwallow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kind of wickedneſſe whatſoever. Thus by his ſubtle arguments drawne from the paucitie of the Elect, the difficulty of being ſaved, at one time, and the Cheapneſſe of mercy at another, he fills his purſe by the ſale of his Spirituall Comforts, and Saints with more confidence and freedome, then that Church he ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes againſt.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Let the dejected drooping penitent <hi>lift up his eies unto the hills from whence cometh his helpe;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 121. 1.</note> and from this text take a fayre proſpect of mercy to his ſaving Comfort: <hi>Behold the Lords hand is not ſhortned, &amp;c.</hi> He hath given thee all the aſſurances of mercy thou canſt propoſe unto thy ſelfe: he hath given thee his Royall word, his Covenant under hand and ſeale, his many ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred proteſtations: nay, he hath bound himſelfe by Oath, to be reconciled, at what time ſoever thou ſhalt turne and repent. Away then with thoſe feares and Jealouſies, that make thee unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of thy makers mercy. The Majeſty of a King is never ſo deeply wounded, as when Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all intentions, and Declarations become blaſted
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155877:8"/> by diſtruſt. And 'tis juſt with God, that they ſhould <hi>forſake their owne mercy,</hi> that dare not truſt it. The truth is, The weakneſſe of our faith, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds commonly from the fouleneſſe of our guilt, and the reaſon why we ſtand in our owne light, and turne our backes upon Gods favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble countenance, is becauſe <hi>our workes are the workes of darkneſſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 19.</note> and therefore we hate that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight that will diſcover them.</p>
            <p>Beware then of ſhortning the good hand of God; Remember <hi>Moſes</hi> at the rocke; <note place="margin">Num. 20. 10.</note> and that great favourite that periſhed at the gate of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 King. 7. 2. 17.</note> by the weight of that mercy he would not beleive. Though more miſcarry by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, yet the more deſperate are they that ruine themſelves by their own deſpair. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>thou ſhalt confeſſe with thy mouth the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and beleive with thine heart that God hath raiſed him from the dead;</hi> (and ſteere thy courſe according to this beleife) thou haſt the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> warrant, <hi>thou ſhalt bee ſaved, Rom.</hi> 10 9.</p>
            <p>In the meane time (for the great extremities we labour under) the ſame Apoſtle aſſures, that God is <hi>able to doe exceeding abundantly for us, above all that we can aske or think.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3. 20.</note> It may ſeeme ſtrange: what? above all that we can aske or thinke? Sure that muſt be a vaſt circumference of mercy, that extends it ſelfe beyond our thoughts; and if deliverances would come with thinking, we could ſoone thinke our ſelves into a better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. But miſtake not; This hand of mercy is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155877:9"/> not held out to every idle, ſquandring thought, every extemporary, indigeſted prayer: but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd to prayers qualified with faith; thoughts regulated by obedience; faſting governed by ſincerity. 'Tis expected all theſe ſhould move from <hi>a pure heart, a good Conſcience, and from faith un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ained.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Wee aske</hi> and <hi>receive not,</hi> and <hi>St James</hi> gives the reaſon, <note place="margin">Jam. 4. 3.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe we aske amiſſe;</hi> we thinke high, and thinke in vaine, becauſe (indeed) we doe little elſe but thinke: wee faſt oft, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrie when all is done; and the reaſon followes in the text, becauſe the obſtruction continues unremoved; Behold <hi>the Lords hand is not ſhortned,</hi> neither <hi>his eare heavy:</hi> but <hi>your iniquities have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated betweene you and your God, and your ſins &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then, what it is that ſeparates. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> makes the <hi>Quoere Rom.</hi> 8. 35. <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate from the love of Chriſt? ſhall tribulation, or anguiſh, or perſecution, or famine, or nakedneſſe, or perill, or ſword?</hi> If theſe would ſeparate, we were but in a very ill condition, as our times now are; by theſe (indeed) faith may ſeeme at ſome time ſtupefied, or as it were ſtrangled for the time, it cannot be extinguiſhed. (as there be many things that will caſt into a traunce, that doe not ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the ſoule from the body) Nothing from without can make this ſeparation, the <hi>Enemies</hi> that muſt doe it, <hi>muſt be of our owne houſe,</hi> of our owne cabinet and familiar acquaintance: the text calls them here by two names, <hi>Sinnes,</hi> and <hi>Iniquities:</hi> (that is) they are ſeverall ſorts of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:155877:9"/> ſinnes, and ſeverall degrees in ſinne: what theſe Iniquities were, and what a miſcheivous influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence they had upon the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> may be ſeene in the verſes immediatly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the text; <hi>Their hands were defiled with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent bloud: their lips blacke with lies: their tongues</hi> furr'd <hi>with murmuring,</hi> their hearts ſo miſchei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous that they <hi>hatch'd Cockatrice eggs:</hi> they <hi>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Spiders web, their feet ſwift to ſhed bloud,</hi> the <hi>way of peace they knew not, they made themſelves crooked paths,</hi> that whoſoever went along with them might not know peace: this the extract of their Sinne; and therefore their puniſhment followes, <hi>They groaped as men without Eyes, and ſtumbled at noone day, they roared all like Lions, and mourned like Doves, and ſate in deſolate places like dead men, &amp;c.</hi> In the ſeventh of <hi>Ier.</hi> 12. God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands his people to take notice what he had done to <hi>Shiloh</hi> (<hi>the place of his name, the dearly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of his ſoule</hi>) <note place="margin">Deut. 12. 11. Jer. 12. 7.</note> onely for the wickedneſſe of thoſe that dwelt there; and the Iudgment wee read of in the firſt of <hi>Sam.</hi> namely, the <hi>Arke</hi> of God (which had continued among them almoſt 300 yeares) was taken by the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> their Preiſts ſlaine, and their people miſerably diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited; 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. 11.</p>
            <p>The time will not give me leave to preſent ye with obſervations taken from Gods dealing with the old world, with <hi>Sodome,</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> with <hi>Egypt, Ninive, Ieruſalem,</hi> with ſome neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Kingdomes of late yeares; or to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155877:10"/> our peace and plenty, with that of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> The light of our knowledge, with that of <hi>Chorazin</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida;</hi> The ſinnes of our nation, with the villany of <hi>Gibeah,</hi> when there fell by the ſword threeſcore and five thouſand; <note place="margin">Jud. 10.</note> The pride of our nation, with <hi>Davids</hi> ambition, when there fell by the peſtilence ſeventy thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand; <note place="margin">2 Sam. 24. 25.</note> The rebellion of our nation, with that of <hi>Corah</hi> and his company, when there fell by the ſame plague 14 thouſand and 7 hundred, beſides thoſe which the fire and a ſtrange death devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <note place="margin">Num. 16.</note> I ſhall onely adde a double aggravation of our ſinnes, wherein we have out-ſtripped all that ever were before us.</p>
            <p>Firſt (as if in all the mire of our forefathers there had, not beene roome enough for us to wallow) we have fulfilled that of the Apoſtle, and have approved our ſelves exquiſite <hi>inventors of evill things, Rom.</hi> 1. 30. Witneſſe our new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions to finde out ſtrange ſinnes, <hi>Peccata ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ena naturae, aliena Gratiae,</hi> monſters in nature, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies in Chriſtianity; witneſſe our new deviſ'd exceſſes in diet and apparell, and our new mint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed oathes and execrations, banded without bluſhing in every corner of our ſtreetes.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, I finde it recorded by the Pſalmiſt (though with no great honour to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi>) <note place="margin">Pſal. 78. 34.</note> that when God ſlew them, then they ſought him, though before they did not; 'Twere well if but ſo much could be ſaid of us; God hath ſlaine us, now almoſt a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155877:10"/> twelve-month together, every day brings in the report of a new ſlaughter ſome where or other, nay very probable it is, that God is ſlaying even whil'ſt I am ſpeaking; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reading, Lich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field. Leedes, Mancheſter,</hi> all beſieged at that time.</note> and yet, I feare, we are yet to ſeeke our God: At firſt (indeed) he only held the rod of his indignation over us, and threatned a long time to ſtrike, that he might not ſtrike at all; and when he did begin to draw bloud, he did it rather like a phyſician, then an executioner. But now, that we have provoked him to draw more bloud, then the body can well ſpare; and ſome of the beſt bloud too; now that the axe is laid to the roote of all that's deare unto us (our Soveraigne, our religion, our lawes, liberties and lives being all in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) Is there an adulterer the leſſe <note place="margin">Prov. 7. 9.</note> 
               <hi>walking in the twilight?</hi> Is there an oath the leſſe, darted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Majeſty of heaven? Is there any abatement of ſinne, any improvement of grace under all our ſtripes? Sure, I may rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the tides of ſinne are farre more high, and overflowing under Judgement, then ever they were under mercy: <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>his mercy</hi> did not <hi>lead us</hi> before, nor doe his Judgements as yet drive us to amendment. And therefore what can we conclude, but that without infinite mercy (the way whereof we cannot ſee in Gods revealed will) our ſinnes are ripe, and we are hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to a ſwift deſtruction. I know this is harſh, and unpleaſing; but I know alſo, that theſe are no times for the pulpit to preſent fine-ſpun opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155877:11"/> as ornaments to be worne only in the eare; <note place="margin">Ezek. 3. 17.</note> 'Tis <hi>the watchmans duty</hi> to give <hi>timely warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and there is a woe reſerved for that ſpiritual phyſician that <hi>skinnes over the wounds</hi> of <hi>Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to their</hi> hurt, <hi>ſaying, Peace, peace,</hi> whil'ſt iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties do ſeparate. <note place="margin">Jer 6. 14.</note> For when the ſword hath done his command, peſtilence and famine ſhall be called in to performe theirs: nay (as if all the written wrath of God were not enough to ſtartle us) the 28 of <hi>Deut.</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>unwritten plagues.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28. 61.</note> So that there ſhall never want a plague to find out that people that ſtand out in rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God; And 'tis little leſſe then Atheiſticall to beleive, that God will give over puniſhing till we give over ſinning.</p>
            <p>So that, as (in the myſtery of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) it was not the malice of the cheife preiſts; nor the blindneſſe of the people; nor the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Pilate;</hi> nor the treachery of <hi>Iudas;</hi> but our ſinnes that drew our Saviour into that dreadfull Agony of his paſſion: ſo in the myſtery of that providence which hangs over us at this day, it is neither the errour, nor treachery of counſels; nor the deſtructive factions &amp; diviſions among themſelves; nor the ignorance of a ſeduced peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and infatuated nation; nor the wild-fire of ſedition, thrown abroad with ſo much art and induſtrie; at all which we ſo much ſtorme and rave; no, Gods meſſenger muſt bid you looke ſome other way, into your ſelves, into your own boſomes: they are your owne iniquities, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155877:11"/> have unhing'd our goodly frames of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and drawne the Church and State into that dreadfull Agony under which it now la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: But <hi>your iniquities have ſeparated, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, wherein God ſeparates. Firſt God withdrawes from a people in the generall, by <hi>withholding all good things from them, Ier:</hi> 5. 25. Such is the naſtie ſtench of ſinne, that it turnes Allmighty God cleane out of his way of mercy, (juſt as a man changes his walke, when he ſees a ſtinking carrion throwne in his way) God will walke with us no longer then wee walke with him, and <hi>if we forſake him, he alſo will forſake us,</hi> 2. <hi>Chron:</hi> 15. 2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God withdrawes, by withholding the preſence of his protection, and <hi>Except the Lord keep the City the watchman waketh but in vain.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal: 127. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</note> When God is ſo highly diſpleaſ'd with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as to put them out of his protection, ſee what follows; <hi>A Lion out of the forreſt ſhall ſlay them, &amp; a Woolfe of the wilderneſſe ſhall deſtroy them, a Leopard ſhall watch over their Cities, becauſe their treſpaſſes are many, and their rebellions are increaſed, Ier:</hi> 5. 6. Of ſo great eſteeme was this preſence of God in <hi>Moſes</hi> his time, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> durſt not march one foote without it; <hi>If thy preſence goe not with us, carrie us not from hence, Exod,</hi> 33: 15.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God may very properly be ſaid to withdraw, when he takes away his Deputies, <hi>the men of his right hand,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal: 80: 17:</note> thoſe viſible Gods to whom he hath entruſted the government of his people. And however, ſome have (more then) thought,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155877:12"/> that thoſe may well enough be ſpared, (and are at this day acting their opinions) yet ſure I am they are not guided by that ſpirit, who hath left it upon record, <hi>for the tranſgreſſions of a land many are the Princes thereof. Prov.</hi> 28. 2. And of thoſe foure things which <hi>Agur</hi> obſerves to breed the greateſt diſquiet in a State, the firſt and cheife is <hi>a Servant when he raigneth,</hi> Prov: 30. 22.</p>
            <p>Fourthly; God withdrawes, by withholding the preſence of his Truth. His Goſpell, and his ordinances are continued, but according as they are uſed. in the Prophet <hi>Jeremies</hi> time, <hi>The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets propheſied lies, and the Preiſts bare rule by the ſword, and the people were very well content, nay they loved to have it ſo, Jer.</hi> 5. laſt; And though <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> were <hi>Iſraells</hi> prophet at that time, whoſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was to pray for them, yet God gives him an expreſſe command to the contrary, <hi>Thou ſhalt not pray for this people, nor lift up a crie, or pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for them. Ier:</hi> 7 16. God hath not ſo entaild his <hi>Goſpell,</hi> or perpetuated his <hi>Church,</hi> to any one place, or people, but that he can remove it when he pleaſes. Tis an herbe will grow in any part of the world under the bleſſing of him that plants it; And when he hath juſt cauſe given him, 'tis very likely he will tranſplant it to a ſoyle that will anſwer the husbandrie he beſtowes upon it. And why not <hi>India</hi> as well as <hi>England?</hi> I dare not ſay, the viciouſneſſe of our lives will totally excuſe their want of faith: yet ſure I am, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſquare of the very <hi>Indians,</hi> is enough to condemne our want of obedience; He that ſaid
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:155877:12"/> 
               <hi>Lo I am with you alwaies, even unto the end of the world;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat: 28: 20:</note> ſaith alſo in another place, <hi>Remember from whence thou art fallen. and Repent, and do thy firſt worke, or elſe I will come quickly, and remove thy can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticke out of his place, except thou repent. Rev.</hi> 2. 5.</p>
            <p>Laſtly (and which includes all the reſt) God withdrawes, by divorcing himſelfe from his people; the phraſe ye have <hi>Ier:</hi> 3. 8. <hi>I gave her a bill of Divorcement</hi> (ſaith God of <hi>rebellious Iſraell</hi>) an expreſſion borrowed from thoſe, who by matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall contract, have lived a long time toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with mutuall joy and comfort, till ſome high miſdemeanour breakes out, which hath noe other remedy but a divorcement. And this ſhould be a word of terror and amazement; for the covenant once diſſolved betweene God and us, our joynture is all forfeited, all the pledges of his love to be returned, <hi>his ſilver and gold, and the faire jewells</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezech: 16: 17:</note> of his wiſedome, grace, and mercy, to be delivered up; A Divorce at once caſheires us of all relations to God; <hi>If any man draw backe, my ſoule ſhall have no pleaſure in him. Heb:</hi> 10. 38.</p>
            <p>And 'tis not <hi>prateritio</hi> (a paſſing by) but <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio,</hi> a word that ſpeakes a farre worſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Better we had never met under the ſame roofe, then to be parted afterwards; Better wee had never <hi>taſted the good word of God, never knowne the way of righteouſneſſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb: 6: 5: 2 Pet: 2: 21:</note> then after the knowledge thereof, to turne away, and forſake it. A Divorce proves ever ſcandalous, to one ſide or other; the memory of a better, doubleth the miſery of a worſe eſtate, and the higheſt aggravation of hels
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155877:13"/> torment lies in <hi>poena Damni,</hi> the remembrance of what we once were, the contemplation of what we might have beene.</p>
            <p>Wee have ſeene how God withdrawes; It were well we would conſider when he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawes too: but herein is our blindneſſe, that God is often with us, by the viſible hand of his mercy and protection, whilſt with ſlumbring <hi>Iacob and Samuel,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen: 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 16: 1 Sam. 3: 7:</note> we are not aware of it: And ſo at other times, God withdrawes and will not go forth with us, nor have any thing to doe with our deſignes, and yet with infatuated <hi>Sampſon,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jud. 16: 20:</note> we are ignorant that <hi>God</hi> and our <hi>ſtrength</hi> are <hi>both depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> that we may therefore be throughly awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to this danger, we are to conſider in the laſt place what condition wee are in, when God is departed from us.</p>
            <p>Whenſoever God departs from a people, or a Citie, or a ſoule, he leaves ſinne, and guilt all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies behind him; <hi>If thou doeſt well ſhalt thou not be accepted?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen: 4: 7:</note> but if otherwiſe <hi>Sinne lies at the doore.</hi> and if Sin lie at the doore, we know what to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from ſuch a porter, namely, That every mercy ſhall be excluded, and every Judgement ſhall be let in upon us.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Eſayes</hi> Judgment ſhall be let in: <hi>I will take away the hedge of my vineyard, and it ſhall be eaten up, and I will breake downe the wall thereof, and it ſhall be troden downe; I will lay it waſte, it ſhall not be cut nor digged, but briers and thornes ſhall grow up, and I will command the cloudes that they ſhall not raine upon it, Eſay.</hi> 5. 5.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:155877:13"/>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Ieremies</hi> Judgment ſhall be let in, <hi>Ier.</hi> 13. 13. <hi>I will fill the inhabitants of Ieruſalem with drunkenneſſe, and I will daſh them one againſt another, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the fathers againſt the ſonnes,</hi> (the juſt character of our unhappy times) brother againſt brother, City againſt City, County againſt County, and yet the deluſion ſo ſtrong, and bewitching, that (with <hi>Demetrius</hi> his rout) <note place="margin">Acts 19: 32:</note> the major part (in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) know not wherefore they are come together.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Malachies</hi> Judgment ſhall be let in, I will not only powre out my Judgments, but <hi>I will curſe even your Bleſſings, yea I have curſed them already, Mal:</hi> 2. 2. Your Invocations ſhall become provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Your Sacraments ſhall return ye charg'd with more guilt: Your Pulpits inſtead of teaching you <hi>to lead a peaceable and quiet life in all godlines and honeſty,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim: 2: 2:</note> ſhall traine you up into rebellion againſt God and your King: And that meeting (ſo long thirſted after to have clinched and faſtned religion and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) ſhall prove a <hi>Petar</hi> (an engine of miſcheife) to teare all in peices. In ſhort, when once our iniquities have driven away our God; that long roll of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that ſtands upon record <hi>Deut:</hi> 28, will (as ſo many writs) be ſerved upon us: every miſcheife will have his full blow at us; &amp; in all this extremity that which ſhould be our ſhelter, will prove our ſnare.</p>
            <p>To ſhut up all; what hath been thus declared in the generall, muſt now be applied to every man in his owne particular. When God is driven out of the heart by ſin, the devill is at that very inſtant invited to come and take poſſeſſion; this <hi>earthly tabernacle</hi> of ours will not be long without a tenant. <note place="margin">1 Sam: 16: 14:</note> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> is not ſooner diſpoſſeſſed of the good, then poſſeſſed of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155877:14"/> the evill ſpirit; and whither that evill ſpirit will lead we may gueſſe if wee looke after the herd of ſwine, <note place="margin">Mar: 5: 13:</note> or rather indeed to a more dangerous lake then that wherein they <hi>periſhed, a lake of fire and brimſtone, where the worme never dieth, nor the fire ſhall ever be quenched.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel: 19: 20: Mar: 9: 43:</note> 
            </p>
            <p>How much then does it concerne us, to ſeparate from that betimes, which otherwiſe, will make an eternall ſeparation betweene God and us? eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in times of hazard, and perplexity; with what confidence might we advance againſt the enemy, were but our drunkennes, our prophaneneſſe, &amp; the poyſon of the whoriſh woman baniſhed our quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? (beſides the ſcandall given to the cauſe) ſure, our ſtrength would not be the leſſe; without queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, our ſucceſſe would be every day more viſible and apparent; <hi>when thou goeſt out with an army,</hi> be ſure to <hi>keepe thee then from all wickedneſſe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Moyſes, Deut:</hi> 23: 9. The meaning is not that wickedneſſe may be diſpenced with at another time; 'tis ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all adviſe tending immediately to thine owne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; for when thou goeſt into the feild, thou goeſt betweene the jawes of death, within the reach of the Cannon, thou art likely enough to take leave of this world; Let not thy mind then be ſo much upon thine honour, or thine enemie, as to forget what ſpirituall armes thou haſt on, to preſerve thy ſoule from eternall ruine. Thou wilt not march out, without thine armes: and wilt thou leave thy God behind thee? He that can ſo eaſily want his God, gives juſt cauſe to ſuſpect, he was never yet throughly acquainted with him.</p>
            <p>'Twas wont to be a proverbe; Let him that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pray go to ſea and learne; and why not into the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:155877:14"/> feild and learne? And yet are the hazards of warre ſo far from ſtartling the military man, that as if (together with his commiſſion) he had a diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be more deſperate, and daring in his ſins, then any other man; he makes Luſt, and Rapine, eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to his profeſſion; the moſt prodigious oathes, but as ſo many neceſſary accents of paſſion belonging to the duty of his place; as if indeed he were reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on Hell, &amp; were practiceing aforehand to curſe &amp; blaſpheme. Beleive it, the weight of Damnation is no whit leſſened, by dandling the name of it upon the tongue; nor can I ſee how they can hope to be preſerved of God who wiſh themſelves confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of him every houre. Though God will not heare the prayers of wicked men, yet 'tis likely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough he will heare their curſes, and bring them home too, <hi>like water into their bowells, and like oyle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their bones;</hi> nay 'tis paſt being likely; 'tis moſt certaine he will, ther's a text for it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109: 18. I know not whether we ſhall more admire, or pitty thoſe bold (not valiant) amongſt us, that dare goe forth to meet their eternall condition, with hearts more hardned, then the Armes that cover them. The cauſe (indeed) requires our lives, it doth not require our ſoules, 'tis no honour to venture them. Nay little do we think how much our evill lives de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, what with our lives we offer to maintaine. 'Tis ſaid in the firſt Pſalme: <hi>That whatſoever the godly man doth it ſhall proſper.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal: 1: 3:</note> Methinkes that ſhould be of great eſteeme (as our times are) that would make e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing to proſper in our hand. Sure it has more vertue, then the <hi>Philoſophers ſtone,</hi> that will turne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing we touch into a bleſſing: and let no man
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:155877:15"/> thinke to proſper otherwiſe; for he that may ſeeme to proſper in his wickedneſſe, may do well to take notice that he lies under the greateſt judgement that can be named on this ſide hell: as having no ſence of judgment till it cannot be reverſ'd, nor ever awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned till the fire be all about his eares. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whil'ſt ye are ingag'd in warre, be ſure ye make your peace with God; and take heed of giving your ſelves that deadly wound, that will never be cured unto all eternity: give no <hi>cauſe to the enemies of the Lord to blaſpheme,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam: 12: 14:</note> and <hi>let not your good be evill ſpoken of,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom: 14: 16:</note> the goodneſſe of your cauſe be ſuſpected and ſullied with the foulneſſe of your ſins: leſt whil'ſt you appeare for your Soveraigne (and in him for your ſelves) by your purſes, and your perſons, ye plat thornes in his crowne ſome other ſecret way, and (unwittingly) wound that righteous cauſe, which cannot, will not thrive, but by holy addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes unto Almighty God.</p>
            <p>It hath been ſhewed, what it is that ſeparates from God: wherein God ſeparates from us: &amp; how miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable we are when God is departed from us. What remaines then? but that we ſo demeane our ſelves in the preſence of God, whil'ſt <hi>his hand is not ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, neither his eare heavy,</hi> that upon all occaſions we may have free and open acceſſe unto his eare: and may find that hand of mercy, (which hath hitherto beene enlarged almoſt to a miracle) conſtant, and propitious, to us and our deſignes. That God may alwaies owne us for his ſervants here in this life, and acknowledge us for his Saints in that which is to come. Which God of his infinite mercy grant, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
